Life is at its most intense during the struggles between predator and prey.
猎手与猎物之间的斗争最能展现生存竞争的激烈
Each side, to survive,
每一方想存活
must outwit and outmanoeuvre the other.
就必须比对方聪明，懂得生存的策略
The prize, for the hunter...a meal.
作为奖励，猎手得到的是一顿美食
For the prey,the chance to live another day.
对于猎物而言，就是能多活一天的机会
Three male cheetahs.
三只雄性的花豹
These brothers are very special.
这三兄弟比较特别
They hunt prey few other cheetahs would dare to tackle.
他们敢于猎杀一些其他猎手不敢碰的猎物
To succeed,they must first select a victim.
要想成功，首先得选择捕猎对象
And then work together to overpower it.
并一起围捕它
It's dangerous work.
这是个危险的活
An adult zebra is potentially lethal.
成年的斑马蹄，是可以致命的
The outcome is by no means certain.
结果是不能预测的
The first cheetah is driven off.
第一只豹被赶走了
And his brothers have already made a critical mistake.
他的兄弟，也犯了一直致命的错误
They aren't close enough to take over the attack.
他们没能靠近猎物，到足够的距离
Each is chasing a different target,
又追向不同的猎物
making it easy for the zebra to defend their young.
这样便于成年斑马保护小斑马
A quarter-tonne stallion finally puts paid to their chances.
250公斤的斑马，终于给他们机会了
Chasing different zebra was bound to lead to failure.
追逐不同的目标，注定是不会成功的
Perhaps their enthusiasm got the better of them.
或者他们的热情比较高涨
They must try again.
他们必须继续尝试
In the shadow of Mount Kenya,the brothers regroup.
在肯亚山的阴影下，兄弟们重新相聚
Their mistake with the zebra was to hunt as ordinary cheetahs do -
他们对斑马的错误策略
as individuals.
和其他豹一样，就是单独追猎目标
To catch such prey, they must hunt like no other cheetahs.
对付这样的猎物，他们必须另想办法
That means acting together, as one.
一起行动
They start again.
他们重新开始了
An ostrich outweighs and outguns a single cheetah.
一只鸵鸟，比任何花豹都要重
This time there's only one target.
这次他们只有一个目标
And all three cheetahs are onto it.
三兄弟一起行动
The third brother starts to throttle the ostrich.
老三，开始袭击鸵鸟
Even off its feet,it's still dangerous.
就算能避开鸵鸟的腿 它依然是一只危险的猎物
The brothers have found a unique way of catching their prey.
兄弟们找到了独有的捕猎方法
The ability to invent such novel hunting tactics
有能力发明这种聪明的捕猎方法
is one thing that really sets mammals apart.
是哺乳类动物，优胜于其他动物
But mammals themselves can also be targets for predators,
但是哺乳类动物 也可能随时成为别人的猎物
and the hunted also need to devise special tactics.
而每一次捕猎，需要采取不同的策略
The desert shores of the Dead Sea.
死海沙漠的边缘
Living here is difficult indeed.
在这里生存，真的是非常困难
It's March, and high on these cathedral cliffs,
现在是三月
ibex have given birth.
在这些高耸的峭壁上 阿尔卑斯 野山羊，在这里生育
For the first few days the kids were kept safe,
最初的日子，小山羊是安全的
isolated on the cliff tops.
有这些悬崖隔离
But now the ibex have a problem.
但是现在他们要面对难题了
The only food and water is far below at the bottom of the gorge.
食物和水源，都远在峡谷的最下面
And that is where predators lurk.
这正是猎食者，潜伏的地方
If they're to feed,it's a risk they will have to take.
他们一定要冒险，才能觅食
The adults lead the way.
成年的山羊领路
They know the safest routes.
他们知道最安全的路线
Though safe, here,is a relative term.
当然这里的安全，只是相对的
The kids have no choice but to keep up.
小山羊，只能紧跟在后
One slip could be the last.
一失足，就可能丧命
Their only assets are cloven hooves that spread under load,
属于偶蹄目的他们 有在这里行走的天赋
astonishing balance...
他们有惊人的平衡能力
..and the most uncanny agility.
加上非常敏捷
Barely a week old,they are utterly fearless.
出生才七天，就天性无畏
Learning to negotiate these cliffs is central to their survival.
学会在悬崖行走 是他们生存的重点
But now the family must be on guard against predators.
现在这家人 必须警惕掠食者了
All grab a chance to browse.
提高每一分警觉
Trailing behind,the last youngster is almost down.
最后一头小羊也来了
And runs right into trouble.
正好遇到麻烦
A fox.
一只狐狸
It's been waiting for the straggler.
这个流浪者在等待
The kid has never seen a fox before, but knows it's in real peril.
小山羊从没见过狐狸，但天性告诉它，这是一个危险
It appears to be running into more trouble,as it heads back up the cliff.
在跑回山上的时候，他遇到更大的麻烦――悬崖
The fox tries to gain the higher ground.
狐狸企图爬上去
But the kid has found safety
但是小山羊找到一个非常陡峭的悬崖
on a face so steep that only an ibex could stand there.
只有阿尔卑斯山羊才能站立在这里
The lessons learnt on this morning's descent have saved its life.
早上下山的时候所学到的一切，救了他一命
Finally, the fox gives it up as a bad job...
狐狸只能放弃这艰难的捕猎
..perhaps suddenly aware it's standing on a precipice.
或者他突然发现自己站在危险的灾难边缘
Despite its tender age, the ibex has outwitted one of the canniest of predators.
就算小小年纪，在这里小山羊的生存智慧还是胜过
The fox's failure epitomises a predator's plight.
狐狸这次失败，显示了猎食者的困境
Most hunts fail,so hunters are continually devising new tactics.
捕猎并不是容易的
The rainforests of Belize in Central America.
在巴西的热带雨林
And as evening falls and the shower comes to an end,
当夜幕低垂，大雨将至
a predator begins to hunt.
一位猎手开始行动
The greater bulldog bat.
巨大的“都牛犬”蝙蝠
A flying mammal...
唯一会飞行哺乳类动物
..and a fisherman.
它是一位“渔翁”
A fish swimming just below the surface creates tell-tale ripples
一条正好游近水面的鱼引起的涟漪
and that is all the bat needs to detect them.
这恰是蝙蝠，需要的信息
With little more than a fin to aim for,
只要一个微弱的抖动
and whilst flying at 40 miles an hour,
这位猎手，以40哩的时速
the bat takes the fish completely unawares.
扑向鱼的位置
If the shoal scatters...
只要浅水有任何震动
..the bat trawls the surface.
掠过水面的蝙蝠
Raking the water,trying to snag a fish.
就会像拖网船一样，大肆捕捞
He won't have the best fishing spot to himself for long,
但有利的捕鱼位置不会很久
and soon, other bats arrive.
其他蝙蝠，很快抵达
Oncoming traffic would make grabbing a fish almost impossible,
繁忙的交通使捕鱼变得几乎“不可能”
so the bats avoid collisions by honking -
他们开始鸣叫，避免碰撞
dropping their calls an octave to say, "Look out, here I come!"
他们争相发出“在这，别撞过来！”
Soon the shoal has either been captured or has fled,
很快，这片浅滩就水泄不通
and the bats move on.
蝙蝠在继续捕捞着…
Skills like this take practice,
这种技巧，是需要实践去锻炼的
and for some mammals that practice begins in infancy.
有些哺乳类，从小就开始实践锻炼
A young stoat.
一只小鼬鼠
And it's not alone.
他不是单独的
These wild game sare too much to resist.
这种野外游戏很吸引它
Stalking, chasing and ambushing,all practised in play.
在游戏中，可以练习埋伏、突击、追逐
Soon the young stoats must hunt for themselves,
很快,小鼬鼠必须自己觅食
and then these athletic skills will be crucial.
而这些技巧是必须的
It's September in the English countryside.
这是九月英国的田野
This stoat is about to take on an adversary ten times its size.
这只小鼬鼠准备对付一个体积十倍的敌人
It's too dangerous to rush straight in.
但直接攻击，是非常危险的
Instead, the stoat's aim is to wear the rabbit down.
然而，小鼬鼠的目的，是消耗兔子体力
The rabbit is flagging,and the stoat's stamina is starting to make a difference.
兔子的力量在衰退，而小鼬鼠的耐力开始使局面发生了变化。
But stamina alone is not enough -the rabbit must still be overpowered.
但是单有耐力还不够，必须有将兔子击倒的攻击才行
A bite to the back of the neck and a kill.
对兔子的颈后的一咬，成为了致命的攻击
The incredible agility of the stoat,practised since it was a kit,
这惊人的准确性，是它在玩耍时就已经学会的技巧
was just enoughb to swing the balance.
这对于它来说，是运用自如
There are times when mere physical powers
有时候，光靠体力是不能战胜对手的
are not enough to give the hunter an edge.
捕猎者要成功，必须有优势
Then mammals must deploy their most sophisticated weapon - their brains.
哺乳类发展了他们的专业――脑袋
Strange patterns are visible in the mud of Florida Bay,
在福罗里达州的海床上，有些奇怪的图案
a faint hint of a unique hunting tactic.
我们可以看到，一种特别的捕猎方法
The perpetrators...
罪犯是
..bottlenose dolphins.
瓶鼻海豚
And they're on a mission -a mission to catch fish.
他们正在准备捕鱼
The fish here are very difficult to catch
这里的鱼是非常难捕获的
and in such shallow water they ought to be safe.
在这种浅水区，他们应当很安全
Yet the dolphins have a plan.
但是海豚们有他们的计划
They have learnt to corral the fish by working as a team.
他们懂得如何分工合作、围捕这种鱼
The lead dolphin beats its tail on the sea bed,
为首的海豚，用尾巴拍打海床
stirring up a ring of mud.
卷起环状的泥土
Trapped inside, the fish take their only way out,
鱼很自然不敢，穿越浑浊的海水
but they're leaping out of the frying pan and into the fire.
他们企图跳出这个 “煎锅”却掉进了“火炉”
Once the mud ring loses its shape,the fish scatter.
一旦短暂的泥圈消失，鱼就大肆逃窜
The dolphins move on and repeat the process.
所以海豚要不断重复这个过程
Brain power combined with team work -it's a winning formula.
运用大脑和团队合作，是制胜的法宝
This behaviour is unique to the dolphins of Florida Bay.
这是福罗里达州海豚，独有的捕猎方法
Successive generations have learnt it from their parents
子女从父母处学习
and in turn they will teach it to their own young.
然后再由他们传授给后代
The ability to pass on such complex behaviours
这种传授复杂技能的行为
is one of the mammals'greatest talents.
是哺乳类动物的天赋
It enables them to survive where others would perish.
这是他们赖以生存的技能
As winter approaches in Alaska,
寒冬正接近阿拉斯加
food gets progressively harder to find.
食物越来越难找
To live here is to walk a tightrope.
在这里生活是非常艰苦的
Yet every year, this coast attracts North America's most impressive hunter.
但是每一年，这片海岸却引来北美洲最厉害的猎手
A brown bear.
棕熊
Here they grow larger than anywhere in the world.
在这里他们比生长在世界任何地方的同类都大
Other bears have also gathered at the edge of the surf.
他们聚集等待
They've come here to fatten up for the winter.
他们是来增肥过冬的
They're waiting for an event that happens just once a year.
他们正等待一年一度的盛宴
The salmon run.
三文鱼大餐
Others will tackle the fish upriver, but here in the sea,
很多熊，选择河流上游，狭窄处等候
these bears have the first chance.
但是，这些熊却捷足先登
Each bear's survival depends on this run of fish staying strong.
冬天，熊的生存，都是靠这些鱼来维持
There are years when their gamble fails and the fish hardly show.
有些年头他们的等待会白费，因为鱼没有出现
Then the bears face starvation.
熊只能面对饥饿
This year promises to be a bumper one
今年他们得到了，丰盛的大餐
and the bears will be able to pile on the pounds ahead of winter.
他们体重大增，以备寒冬
Mammals are supreme in their ability to exploit such fleeting opportunities.
哺乳类动物很懂得利用这种团体的力量
Chances come and go with the passing of the seasons.
盛宴终止，冬天降临
But for some predators, conditions are tough whatever the time of year.
但对于某些捕猎者而言，每一年都是非常艰苦的
At first glance, these mountains seem barren and empty of life.
看上去，这些山岭似乎是渺无生命
Like islands thrust up into the sky,
像是漂浮于云中的岛屿
they tower above the surrounding plains.
他们突出在附近的高原
Yet, far from being deserted,they are a refuge.
其实他们是避难所
Isolated here,on the roof of Africa,
在这被隔离的非洲屋脊
is one of the rarest hunters in the world.
有世界上罕见的猎手
The Ethiopian wolf.
埃塞俄比亚狼
The only wolf in the whole of Africa.
非洲唯一的狼
Despite being close to the equator,these peaks are so cold at night
就算处于赤道，这些山峰的晚上还是很冷的
that the wolves face a frost-covered dawn.
狼，面对着霜冻的清晨
Each pack is centred around a single dominant female.
每一群狼都由一位成年的女皇带领
Normally it is only she who breeds.
通常只有一头母狼负责生育
This year she has produced six pups.
这一年，她生了六只小狼
But if she is to raise them all in this barren land,
但是如果她要在这荒芜之地，让他们全部存活
she will need the help of the entire pack.
她就需要整群狼的帮助
Every morning,the pack sets off to hunt,
每个早上，狼群出发捕猎
leaving her back among the rocks with the pups.
只留下她，在石堆中照顾小狼
The pack's hunting ground is about five square miles of mountain top.
他们在山上，大概5平方英里内捕猎
They guard it zealously,
他们把狩猎场围个水泄不通
patrolling its frontiers every day.
每天巡逻边界
Wolves elsewhere co-operate
他们密切合作
and use their united power to pull down big prey.
是企图猎杀大猎物？
But there are no caribou or moose to be found up here.
但是这里没有巨大的唇鹿
The pack splits up.
他们分开
Each member is going to hunt alone.
首先单独狩猎
One of them spots something.
其中一位发现了什么？
It's a rat.
小老鼠
But catching rats is not easy, no matter how carefully you stalk them.
无论你如何隐蔽捕捉老鼠，不是件容易的事
Another hunter has a more pro-active technique.
他们发明了更主动的方法
RAT SCREECHES And that works.
成功了！
It's a lot of work for relatively small rewards,
花这么大力气，换来小小的收获
and demands its own particular style of hunting.
还要这种独特的狩猎技巧
A hunter returns.
一位猎手回来了
Mother demands food and the successful hunter delivers it.
猎手捐出了，母狼索要的食物
So rearing a single litter here
尽管是这么小的一份
takes the combined labour of a dozen or so adults
但，这是集体的力量
and the Ethiopian wolves have adjusted their behaviour accordingly.
这就是狼，得以生存的策略调整
That adaptability is the mammals' great strength,
适应环境，也是哺乳类动物的强项
enabling them to survive in some very unlikely habitats.
这令他们在这种好像不能生存的环境中存活下来
A star-nosed mole,
一只星鼻鼹鼠
possessor of perhaps the most extraordinary nose on the planet.
他具有可能是这地球上最独特的鼻子
Its nostrils are surrounded by twenty-two fingers.
他的鼻孔，有22只手指状的组织
Fingers that allow the mole to sense the world around it by touch alone.
这让他仅凭这些手指与外界的接触，就足以获得外界的信息
It enables it to detect food with astonishing speed.
通过接触他就可以用惊人的速度找到猎物
It can also swim...
他会游泳
..and once underwater, its nose helps it in a most extraordinary way.
在水中，他不平凡的鼻子也能帮助他
It blows out a bubble and breathes it back in,
它吹出一个气泡又吸回
detecting in a millisecond if there's prey close by.
能用1/1000秒来侦测附近的猎物
This bubble-blowing allows it to sniff out its food underwater,
这种方法能让他在水中寻找食物
but, unfortunately, that means it soon runs out of breath.
但这很快使他的氧气储备用完
So it's just as well that it can hunt as fast down here as on the surface.
所以他要很敏捷地去捕猎
Few creatures can hunt equally successfully underground and underwater.
很少动物能如此迅速地捕猎
Bandhavgarh, India,
印度，宾达威格 国家公园
at the height of the dry season.
在最干旱的季节
A chital deer.
一只印度梅花鹿
They must live their lives with all their senses at a high pitch.
他必须分分秒秒都保持警惕
The faintest smell,
最微弱的气味
the slightest sound,
再细小的声音
the briefest glimpse
最迅速的一瞥
could give warning of an attack.
观察是否有危险
The chital must detect their enemy
梅花鹿发必须发现它们的敌人
before it takes them by surprise.
在它们突袭自己以前
And they have allies.
他们有盟友
Langur monkeys.
灵猴
Keen eyesight and a perch high in the trees
好的眼力和有利的地形
means they can scan the forest.
他们能观察到整个森林
The jungle is full of distraction.
森林会充满，各种分心的事情
Senses are strained,trying to detect approaching danger.
高度紧张地，防止危险的发生
Yet the chital still need to feed.
一群梅花鹿
And the hunter must get within striking distance.
猎手，要缩短伏击的距离
There's a hint of danger carried on the wind.
在风中有一丝危险的提示
The herd shares a nervousness.
他们分外紧张
You should never run from what you can't see,
其实不应该跑，你并没有看见猎手
you might just run straight into danger.
这样只会令你，走向另一个危险
The tiger is nearly close enough to launch her attack.
老虎已经靠的够近了
She must wait.
但是她必须等待
The chital need to come just a little closer.
再靠近一点
If she moves now,the langurs will see her.
但是她再靠近，就会被灵猴发现
The deer had a moment's head start,and escape.
梅花鹿发现并跑掉了
The langurs' vigilance saved the chital.
警觉的灵猴，救了梅花鹿
And the tiger goes hungry.
老虎只能挨饿了
For some mammals,attack is the best form of defence.
对于有些哺乳动物来说，攻击是最好的防御
This squirrel is arming herself.
松鼠在武装自己
It's a California ground squirrel,and she's found a snake skin.
这只加利福尼亚，地松鼠发现了蛇皮
She's chewing it into a paste
她把它嚼烂，并擦涂在身上
which she then rubs into her fur,especially her tail.
尤其是她的尾巴
She now stinks of snake.
现在，她身上有一般蛇的气味
She lives in a colony that extends across a wide expanse of prairie.
她生存的地方，包括草原和牧场
There is one downside to this neighbourhood -
另外，在她生活地方
it's in the middle of rattlesnake country.
也是响尾蛇，居住的地方
Not good when you have young to raise.
尤其当你要抚育后代时
Her neighbour has sensed something.
她的邻居好像感觉到什么
A rattlesnake,hidden right next to their burrow.
一条响尾蛇，就住在他们洞穴的附近
They both investigate but what can they do?
他们会如何做呢？
Kicking stones only provokes the snake.
这会激怒响尾蛇
Rattlesnakes sense prey by the heat they give off
在千钧一发的时刻
and the squirrel is able to take advantage of this.
松鼠会利用
She heats up her tail with warm blood.
他，竖起的蓬松尾巴
Waving it at the snake is a threat.
不断摆动，来恐吓响尾蛇
It makes her look much larger than she is.
这使她看上去，体型更大
And the scent of rattler on her fluffed tail
而且她尾巴上的气味，更像是蛇
intimidates the snake.
她竟然在模仿响尾蛇
It decides to retreat.
蛇决定撤退
The mother decides this part of the neighbourhood is too dangerous,
然而，松鼠感到住在这里太危险了
and moves her young to new quarters.
她搬家了
With luck, this may be a safer place to raise a family.
如果幸运，新的居所，可能是理想的
Both predator and prey must endlessly refine their strategies.
猎手和猎物，都必须不断地精研他们的策略
Just occasionally, an individual makes a unique breakthrough
偶而, 一些动物会有突破性的策略
and learns to do something completely new.
掌握了一些崭新的技巧
It's December, and a storm rages around the Falkland Islands.
12月，寒风凛冽的福克兰群岛
Gentoo penguins face blizzards of blown sand.
巴布亚企鹅，面对暴风雪和沙石
Young elephant seals risk being dragged off the rocks by the surging waves
小海象，在危险的岩石边
and swept out into open water.
被汹涌的海浪冲入海里
Orca - the largest and most predatory of the dolphin family.
虎鲸，一种大型的海洋动物
Killer whales.
我们熟悉的杀人鲸
This pod of nine can only survive here by being opportunists.
这群虎鲸，共有九条。要在这里生存，必需抓紧机会
Normally, young elephant seals are not on the menu.
一般来说，小海象并不是菜单上的猎物
They stay close to the shore,safe in the shallows of their nursery pool.
他们一般远离大海
The pool is almost entirely cut off from the sea.
在他们的抚育场所
A narrow, shallow channel is the only access to the open water.
由一处窄长的浅水地带连接
But this pod of killer whales contains a very special female.
但是这群杀人鲸里，有一条特别的雌性
She's easily identified by her calf,which is always close by.
她带着幼鲸
Every year she comes to the pool at the same time,
每年她都会来这里
when the seals first swim in the shallows.
当海狮游进浅海
She knows how to get them.
她就懂得如何去捕获他们
Negotiating the channel is her first challenge.
穿过狭窄的水道，是她的第一个挑战
The water near the mouth of the pool is slightly deeper.
在小水滩开口处的水，刚好比较深
Here she sets her ambush,
她就在这里伏击
waiting for a seal to stray out of the shallows.
等待海狮游到深水处
For mother and calf,this is an extremely risky ploy.
对于这位母亲和她的幼子来说这是危险的
She must continuously assess how big the waves are, how deep the water is
她必须不断地衡量海浪的大小
and what the tide is doing.
水的深浅、和潮汐的涨落
One bad decision would see both mother and calf stranded.
稍有不慎，她们将会搁浅
The seals lie in the shallows,
海狮在浅水处，还离她们很远
just out of reach and unaware of her presence.
也没察觉，他们的到来
But she is more than aware of the dropping tide.
不过她不单只在衡量海浪的变化
A floundering seal catches her attention...
惊慌失措的海狮，引起了他们的注意
..and with her calf,she slowly moves towards it.
因为带着幼鲸，他比较谨慎地靠近浅水区
The seal is lying right on the edge of a rocky ledge,
海狮正好躺在岩石的突出处
oblivious to the danger.
危险得很
The projecting ledge keeps the seal just out of reach.
这伸延突出的岩石，使杀人鲸无法靠近
Yet she has a plan.
但是她已经有个计划
Rocking back and forth,she's making a wave,
前后移动，她制造波浪
trying to wash the seal off the ledge.
以便把海狮，冲出这块岩石
But it is securely surrounded by kelp.
但是海草的存在，增加了难度
A splash alerts her to a better opportunity.
一个浪花提醒了她，她有更好的主意
Another seal has started to swim into the pool.
另一只海狮开始游进这个小水滩
This is her chance.
她的机会来了
Edging further into the shallows than ever before,she's risking everything.
她冒着危险，游到浅水区
Half beached and with a struggling seal in her mouth,
冲上沙滩，将海狮咬到嘴里
it takes all her strength to drag it out of the pool.
再用尽全力把他拖下水
She is the only killer whale on the planet
她是在这地球上唯一懂得这样
that knows how to hunt these seals in this way
捕杀海狮的杀人鲸
and, crucially, she's now passing on that skill to her own calf.
重要的是，她现在正传授给幼鲸这个技巧
Extraordinary strategies like these
这样巧妙的策略
lie at the heart of the struggle between predator and prey.
驱使着每一个猎手和猎物
They're born of a conflict that is relentless and unforgiving.
他们要生存，就得适应大自然的无情
A conflict that eternally binds the hunter and the hunted.
命运把猎手和猎物，紧紧地联系起来
It's looking very promising.
将来看似充满希望
The Life team had set themselves a tough challenge
BBC Life 团队订立了一个艰难的目标给自己
in trying to film exceptional hunting sequences,
在拍摄这些非常的捕猎场面
but our teams were lucky enough
但是他们很幸运
to observe some of the world's most charismatic predators.
他们有机会观察到世界上最有趣的捕猎者
It was the killer whales of the Falklands, though,
看看这些福克兰群岛的虎鲸
that brought the team closest to the action.
带领着摄制队，到达了最近的拍摄地点
Every year, off Sea Lion Island,
每一年在这海狮岛上
killer whales snatch young elephant seals from their nursery pool.
杀人鲸都会把幼小的海狮拖下海
Filming most hunting sequences involves
拍摄这些镜头
a great deal of waiting and a slice of luck,
通常需要相当的耐心和一点幸运
but here things were a little different.
但是在这里事情有点不同
Cameraman Mike Pitts and producer Adam Chapman travelled to the Falklands
摄影师和制作人，远渡福克兰群岛
having heard that, for two weeks each year,
他们听说这里，每年当中有二个月
killer whales focuson one particular spot.
杀人鲸会到来
The killer whales have learnt to target elephant seal pups
杀人鲸懂得寻找年幼的海象作为目标
as they first venture into the water
而且是当他们第一次下水时
and this gives the team their best chance of filming a hunt.
这样摄制组就有充分的时间去拍摄
The first task facing the team is to familiarise themselves not only with a new location
摄制队第一时间不但要熟悉这个拍摄场地
but also with the animals they will be working around.
还要熟悉这些被拍摄的对象
And the team soon realise that they and their equipment
摄制组很快发觉，他们和拍摄仪器
are a great novelty to the seal pups.
对小海象来说显得很新奇
I daren't look into the camera
我宁愿在镜头看他们
because I'm more worried about the tripod being knocked over.
因为我担心，脚架被他们撞倒
We've got a little friend here
看，我们的小朋友来了
so I'm gonna report him for interfering with the film crew.
我要投诉他们妨碍拍摄
The pups' fascination with the team is rather unexpected.
小海象的好奇心令我们意外
You've got a great way with wildlife, Michael!
麦克，你对野生动物真有办法
At one with nature!
适应环境咯
It's quite difficult out here.There's so many of them.
啊... 这里有点麻烦，就是他们实在太多了
The large number of youngsters bodes
大量的幼海象
well for the killer whales,
对于杀人鲸来说是好事
but the longerthe team spend with the pups,
我们与小海象，相处越久
the more they warm to them.
我们就越喜欢他们
When you look at these little pups
当你看着这些小海象
you can't fail to be captivated by them,
你一定会被他们吸引
especially when you gaze into those eyes,
尤其是当你注视他们的眼睛时
it really pulls on your heartstrings,
他们真的能牵动你的心
but for an orca, of course,
但是对于杀人鲸
it's 120 kilos of pure protein,
他们只是20公斤的蛋白质
so that's why they're hunted.
所以杀人鲸在这里猎食
As the days go by,
日子越久
the team continue to get a feel for the location,
摄制组对这里的感情就越深
when suddenly the killer whales arrive.
突然间，杀人鲸抵达了
The pod of nine is clearly interested in the pool,
显然他们对这里，非常感兴趣
and one female is particularly confident.
一条雌性杀人鲸，特别的自信
She's coming in.
她来了
The female and her calf start to come into the pool regularly,
她和她的幼鲸，经常来这里
but there never seems to be a pup within reach.
但是她们碰不到，远处的猎物
The team have come to the Falklands prepared to film underwater.
我们来福克兰是准备在水底拍摄的
Now the time has come to see if this is a realistic ambition.
现在应该重新考虑一下，这个决定是否现实
With lookouts posted and the whales far away
杀人鲸在远方出现
Mike is able to get in.
摄影师就算能靠近
Even so,
就算这样
who can blame him for being jumpy?
谁能责怪它那么紧张呢？
The pups' playfulness is becoming an issue -
小海狮贪玩，对我们造成了困难
the last thing the team want is
最后有件事摄制队希望
to have any influence on the events they're here to film.
他们的拍摄，不会对这里的生态造成影响
There's also the question of how the killer whales might react
这也取决杀人鲸的反应
to a person in the water.
对于在水里面的人来说
It's quite intimidating in there.
这里非常的合适
It shelves up, so I'm in the centre of the channel and it goes down to,
这里有个突出的地方
I don't know, maybe eight feet I think
我拿不准，估计这里有8丈
a couple of metres.
大概有个几米
But the visibility's really stirred up.
但海水的能见度非常差
How they find their way in that channel I just don't know.
他们怎么找到这条通道，真的不太清楚
And what I'm worried about is if I do get in the water with the orca...
我非常担心 如果我同事和杀人鲸进入这水道
Which I'm slightly concerned about,I have to say...
因为要在水里，等上一段时间
She's in a hunting mode,she's not here just for her to pass the time of day.
杀人鲸是来觅食的，而不是来度假
She's out there to kill something,
她是来杀戮的
and, you know, I just don't want to be that person, or seal...
大家都知道，我担心自己成为猎物
Whatever she thinks I am.
无论她怎样看待我
She'll probably realise once she's bitten me that she's made a mistake
有可能咬我一口，才发现咬错了对象
and, I don't know,is it worth the gamble?
我不知道，这是否值得我赌上性命
With a week already gone,
一周快要过去了,
the killer whales have not yet made a full-blown attack,
杀人鲸还是没有再游回来
and then the weather changes.
天气起了变化
Well, hopefully it'll blow itself out but I think ...
或许它会到别的地方,但我认为
The pool, it's going to be a couple of days before that calms down.
这个地方，会平静一段时间
The storm rages for two more days,
这风暴持续了二天
but on the eleventh day the good weather returns.
十一天后，恢复了好天气
Mike knows that time is running out.
时间紧迫
Well, the orcas are out there,they're still quite a way off.
而杀人鲸还是，离这里很远
The team decides a camera on the end of a pole
摄制组，决定放一台摄影机到杆上
might be the way to reveal the underwater action.
希望这能帮助拍摄水底的情况
After that storm,it's been so stirred up.
暴风过后，海底依然浑浊
And just... Just bring it slightly out of the water, Adam,
我们要将它稍微贴近水面
so draw it back towards you and stop.
拉……好……停！
And it's dark, dark, green,basically, very dark green.
基本上很黑，漆黑一片
There's still a lot of...Suspension, yeah.
仍有许多...悬浮物，是的没错
The storm had stirred up the pool
风暴把海水搞的很浑浊
making it hard to see anything, but the team remain in good spirits.
使我们很难看见任何东西 但我们还是保持很高的热情
Does my bum look big in this? Massive!
穿这个我的屁股是不是显得很大? 确实很强大!
As the seal pups are nearly ready to go to sea,
当小海狮准备第一次下海时
the whales' opportunity to hunt this year will soon pass
杀人鲸，捕猎的时间，已经变得很少了
and the team know this could be their last chance.
摄制组知道，这可能是最后的机会
Look at the size of that fin!
看看鳍的尺寸
OK, Mike, she's coming in. She's coming in, Mike.
好了，麦克, 她来了
She's coming in? Just here.
来了？这里吗？
Mike?
麦克？
One second, mate.
等等
I can talk to you gently here now
这里可以了，我可以和你对话了
and I can also see where you're pointing.
我看见你指的了
She's in.
她来了
I'm recording.Hold it steady, hold it steady.
我正在录，慢慢，稳定！
I got it.
拍到了
She's gone past, Mike,she's in the pool.
她通过了，她到达了浅水
OK, get in there.
好！ 我要过去了
She's got one, definitely,you can't mistake it.
她抓到一个，别错过了
Bringing it out now.Taking it straight out.
带走它，带远一点，快！
She's pulling it out.
拖它离开
Out to sea...
拖下海里面
Taking it under.
她把它拖下去了
God, he just got hammered.
上帝, 它被拖走了
Part of me's elated that I've got it,but part of me's sad, really,
我觉得非常兴奋，不过又有点悲伤…真的
cos I've watched these little characters,
因为我看着，这些小海狮
these pups grow in the last few weeks
这些天，看着她们成长
and the orcas too,they've got to survive and they've made a successful hunt
然而虎鲸也一样，他们只是进行了一次成功的狩猎
and they're now continuing their journey, so what can you say?
他们现在去继续他们的旅程了，我们能说些什么呢？
Witnessing such events often results in such a conflict of emotions.
亲眼目睹这类事情，我们常常会感概万千
The two-week window is over and the killer whales move on.
二个星期的拍摄完成了，虎鲸也离开了
It'll be a whole year before this exceptional female
要一年后，她们才会再来这里
returns here to hunt again.
再开杀戒